<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="actividad1">Play dress up with Pinto according to your role and explain to your classmates why you chose those clothes and objects.</string>
    <string name="actividad2">Which area of the settlement would your character have spent the most time in? Play the maze taking that place as the goal and complete the information provided with what you remember from the visit.</string>
    <string name="actividad3">Team up with classmates who share your role and find out what made you indispensable for the functioning of a Vaccean village. Then, present your work to your classmates.</string>
    <string name="lanzas">Spears were very popular weapons in my time. They were made of wood with an iron tip and we used them for fighting and hunting animals. Warriors carried them into battles because they were strong and easy to use. Additionally, spears were a symbol of bravery and power, and we often included them in warriors\' graves to show respect. They were key tools in our daily life and traditions.</string>
    <string name="pulseras">Bracelets were very popular ornaments in my village. We made them from metals like bronze, iron, or gold, and some were beautifully decorated with patterns or special shapes. They were not just for decoration but also to show our status, especially for warriors and important people. Some bracelets were also used in rituals or ceremonies. Vacceans believed bracelets could bring good luck or protection; they were amulets. Archaeologists have found bracelets we included in funerary goods, and it seems they liked them a lot!</string>
    <string name="azadas">Hoes were tools commonly used by our farmers, mainly for working the land. We made them from wood, with a stone or metal blade. They were used to loosen the soil, dig, and weed crops, helping with daily agricultural tasks like sowing and preparing the land. Hoes were also used in gardens and small fields. Being a manual tool allowed us to ensure personally that the soil was well-cultivated and ready for harvesting.</string>
    <string name="copas">Cups were one of the basic objects in our tableware, like your favorite mug! We made them from ceramic and sometimes metal. They had simple shapes, but many were decorated with animal drawings or geometric patterns. We used them for drinking but also in ceremonies or rituals, such as feasts or funerals. Some cups were placed in graves as we believed they would be needed in the afterlife. My people learned to make pottery in a very beautiful and unique way, and I’m very proud of it.</string>
    <string name="espada">Ah, my sword! It\'s made of iron with a straight double-edged blade. The more beautiful the decorations on the hilt, the better. My favorites are geometric patterns, but there are also animal designs. In addition to fighting, swords are symbols of power and wealth. Warriors carried them to their graves because they are very important to us. Thanks to our interactions with other cultures, we know they are similar to those used in other parts of the world.</string>
    <string name="fibula">Fibulae were metal brooches we used to fasten and decorate our garments. These pieces were made of bronze and other metals like silver and gold. The more important the person, the better the materials they could use. Among the most popular designs were Hispano-Roman annular fibulae with circular designs. Many were decorated with geometric and figurative designs, like wolf heads.</string>
    <string name="pendiente">My earring! Oh, I thought I’d lost it. Yes, Vaccean men also wore earrings. In fact, we even had earlobe stretches to fit earrings through. We wore them not just to look handsome but also to demonstrate our social class to our neighbors. In my village, we had very skilled artisans capable of creating beautiful pieces with various types of metals. I’m very proud of their work.</string>
    <string name="jarra">Did you know that the Vacceans made wine? For that, we needed jars. The jars were made of clay and were smooth, sometimes painted in dark brown with geometric shapes and patterns. The color wasn’t paint but oxide, achieved by regulating the oxygen level in the kilns; more oxygen resulted in more orange and less oxygen resulted in more black. In other cases, we used incision techniques, removing small pieces of clay with a knife before firing them.</string>
    <string name="canica">Marbles! I loved my marbles, we made them out of clay, and they were very small. In some cases, we decorated them using various techniques like stamping, painting, or carving. As a child, I played with them by throwing them at things and practicing my aim.</string>
    <string name="sonajero">This is a rattle. They were closed containers with little balls inside that made sounds when shaken. We made them in various shapes with unique decorations, featuring geometric or animal figures. To make them, we enclosed the balls in clay pieces and sometimes added powder to prevent them from sticking. When shaken, they sounded like a baby’s rattle and were used in rituals to make music.</string>
    <string name="caja">Ceramic boxes were common in my village. Artisans made them from very fine clay. They started with a block of clay that they cut and hollowed to shape. These pieces were usually strong and decorated with carvings on three sides, leaving the side with the handle plain. Many boxes were shaped like animals, such as horses or bulls, with their handles modeled accordingly. My favorite is shaped like a deer.</string>
    <string name="escudo">The shields we used in my village were round, made of wood and covered with leather, to protect us in combat. They were large to cover as much of the body as possible. Often, they had metal reinforcements on the edges for durability. The designs on our shields were simple to keep them functional, but some might include personalized designs to identify tribe members or warrior gods.</string>
    <string name="facil">EASY</string>
    <string name="medio">MEDIUM</string>
    <string name="dificil">HARD</string>
    <string name="completado">COMPLETED!</string>
    <string name="muralla">Thanks for taking me to the wall! Walls were key elements in defending my village and improving the organization of space. Archaeologists working in Pintia have uncovered the defensive structures that protected us from the outside and are making them look beautiful. Our walls were built with local materials like stone and earth, and their main function was to protect the community from attacks, especially from nearby tribes or enemy groups. It’s not always easy to get along with neighbors!</string>
    <string name="cenizales">Cremation sites give me the creeps! This is where we carried out burnings, either for the destruction of corpses or for rituals. In Pintia, this area was built near the Las Ruedas cemetery because when we finished burning our dead, we buried the remains along with important objects. Only warriors, who were strong and brave, were spared from burning, as their bodies were offered to vultures, and young children were buried in their homes.</string>
    <string name="pueblo">My village is so beautiful! Pintia is a fortified settlement with houses of circular or rectangular shape. We worked hard to adapt them to the daily needs of my friends and organized the space with a focus on defense, although we also had social structure-based separations. Around the village, we had areas for artisans, like potters, showing that we were a self-sufficient community.</string>
    <string name="necro">I thought we wouldn’t make it! The necropolis is fundamental to understanding my people’s beliefs, and it’s where we buried our dead. In the graves, we included funerary goods made up of weapons, jewelry, and other objects, reflecting the deceased\'s social status. It was also essential to include useful items for their new life after death, like kitchenware or “inheritances.” For us, these weren’t just burial places but also associated with rituals and ceremonies tied to our religious and spiritual beliefs.</string>
    <string name="barrio">In Pintia, we had an outer area dedicated to pottery making, where my friends and I crafted our ceramic tools and objects. These workshops or "neighborhoods" were specialized zones. We were a well-organized and very productive people! Archaeologists studying my people have found high-quality ceramic fragments and understood that my town was full of skilled and talented people capable of producing useful and decorative items.</string>
    <string name="pajaro">For us, birds had a special meaning! They represented the connection between earth and sky, and we thought they could help guide our souls to another world. We also saw birds as symbols of protection and good luck, especially in times of war. We placed bird drawings on ceramics and urns used in important ceremonies. So, for my people, birds were much more than animals; they were symbols of spiritual help and guidance.</string>
    <string name="gallo">Roosters were beloved animals in my village. They were much more than just birds! They appeared on stones and sculptures that decorated tombs because we believed they helped the souls of the dead travel to the sky. Since roosters crow at dawn, they also symbolized the beginning of a new day, a rebirth. We saw them as protectors and spiritual guides. Sometimes, we drew them on objects like ritual vessels. This animal represented the connection between life and death, bringing strength and hope to my people.</string>
    <string name="caballo">Horses were very important to us. They appeared in drawings, stones, and objects as symbols of power and wealth. Only chiefs or important warriors had horses, and sometimes they were buried with them upon death. We used them for battle, fast travel, and fieldwork. In our drawings, horses are often depicted with warriors, showing how strong they were together. Additionally, these animals held special significance in ceremonies and beliefs. They were much more than companions!</string>
    <string name="buitre">Vultures were highly valued animals by my people. In our drawings and decorations, we used vultures as symbols of death and the sky. These birds, which feed on dead animals, helped represent how people’s souls ascended to the sky. We believed vultures guided the spirits of fallen warriors. They also appear on decorated stones to commemorate their feats. To us, vultures were not frightening but special and meaningful.</string>
    <string name="lobo">A wolf! For my people, the wolf was a very important animal representing strength, cunning, and bravery. While wolves were sometimes dangerous for our livestock, we respected them greatly and believed they could symbolize protection. Wolves were included in various everyday objects like oven covers and fibulae, as well as funerary items to guard and protect our deceased. We also thought wolves were special and capable of communicating between the earthly and spiritual worlds.</string>
    <string name="tintin">My old Tintinnabula! I used this to keep evil spirits away from my home. We made them out of ceramics, consisting of a rectangular plate with holes in the corners where we would pass rings. Then, we chose a good tree near our house to hang it. We just had to wait for the wind to blow and the rings to jingle. The name comes from that tinkling sound, isn\'t that curious?</string>
    <string name="nivelPuzzle">PUZZLES........................</string>
    <string name="nivelLaberinto">MAZE.............................</string>
    <string name="nivelExcavar">DIG..................................</string>
    <string name="enhorabuena">Congratulations!</string>
    <string name="finalizar">FINISH</string>
    <string name="fintest">End of the test!</string>
    <string name="instrucciones">Drag anywhere in the maze to move Pinto between the squares.</string>
    <string name="entendido">GOT IT!</string>
    <string name="enunciado">Find the 4 buried objects!</string>
    <string name="guerreros">You are part of the Brave Warriors:\n Imagine ancient superheroes. These were the Vaccean warriors. They protected our village from animal attacks, neighboring tribes, and sometimes even imperial armies like those pesky Romans. Because they were so strong and brave, they belonged to the highest social classes and had many jewels and fine clothing.</string>
    <string name="campesino">You are part of the Hardworking Farmers:\n If you love the outdoors and animals, this is for you. These friends grew wheat, barley, and vines, among other things, as if they had a giant garden. They also took care of livestock, usually chickens, sheep, and cows. Thanks to them, everyone in the village had tasty food and warm clothes all year round.</string>
    <string name="consejero">You are part of the Wise Advisors:\n Just like our friends or parents give us good advice, my advisor friends were a very beloved and respected figure. They helped everyone make important decisions and told fascinating stories about the past. Some even knew about medicine and how to play instruments.</string>
    <string name="artesano">You are part of the Creative Artisans:\n Do you like crafts? My artisan friends were experts in that. They worked with metal in forges, textiles on looms, and were skilled potters. Thanks to their hard work, everyone in the village had tools, toys, clay plates, jewelry, and clothes. This way, we all had unique and original items!</string>
    <string name="qgenero">Are you a boy or a girl?</string>
    <string name="qpreferencia">What do you prefer?</string>
    <string name="qgusta">What do you like the most?</string>
    <string name="qmayor">What do you want to be when you grow up?</string>
    <string name="qjugar">How do you like to play with your friends?</string>
    <string name="qorganizar">How do you like to organize your day?</string>
    <string name="qimportante">What is the most important thing to you when playing?</string>
    <string name="qdificil">What do you do when something is difficult?</string>
    <string name="qfin">What makes you feel good at the end of the day?</string>
    <string name="chica">Girl</string>
    <string name="chico">Boy</string>
    <string name="campo">Countryside</string>
    <string name="ciudad">City</string>
    <string name="equipo">Playing team games</string>
    <string name="mascotas">Being with my pets or taking care of plants</string>
    <string name="compras">Going shopping</string>
    <string name="manualidades">Doing crafts, drawing, or building</string>
    <string name="militar">Soldier</string>
    <string name="jardinero">Gardener</string>
    <string name="presidente">President</string>
    <string name="alfarero">Potter</string>
    <string name="competir">Playing games where we can compete or work together</string>
    <string name="deportes">Outdoor sports</string>
    <string name="estrategia">Playing board or strategy games</string>
    <string name="ensenar">Teaching my friends things I know how to do and creating them together</string>
    <string name="listo">I like being ready for any fun thing that might happen</string>
    <string name="aburrirme">I like having many things to do so I don\'t get bored</string>
    <string name="horario">I prefer having a schedule where I can play and rest</string>
    <string name="proyectos">I like having time to work on my projects</string>
    <string name="decisiones">Making decisions as a team</string>
    <string name="rapido">Finishing the game quickly and doing it well</string>
    <string name="contentos">Making sure everyone is happy and having fun</string>
    <string name="divertido">Creating something myself that is fun</string>
    <string name="pienso">I think a little before trying to do it</string>
    <string name="resolver">I try to solve it quickly without thinking too much</string>
    <string name="analizar">I analyze the situation well and then decide what to do</string>
    <string name="buscar">I find a creative way to solve it</string>
    <string name="fuerte">Having finished a tough game and feeling strong</string>
    <string name="orden">Knowing I took good care of my things and everything is in order</string>
    <string name="amigo">Knowing I helped a friend</string>
    <string name="genial">Seeing something I made with my hands that looks great</string>
    <string name="app_name">Juego</string>
    <string name="colorear_button">PAINT</string>
    <string name="puzzle_button">PUZZLE</string>
    <string name="laberinto_button">MAZE</string>
    <string name="excavar_button">DIG</string>
    <string name="crucigrama_button">CROSSWORD</string>
    <string name="perfil_button">PROFILE</string>
    <string name="ajustes_button">SETTINGS</string>
    <string name="home_button">HOME</string>
    <string name="siguiente_button">NEXT</string>
    <string name="anterior_button">BACK</string>
    <string name="horizontales">HORIZONTALS:</string>
    <string name="verticales">VERTICALS:</string>
    <string name="a1">ACTIVITY 1</string>
    <string name="a2">ACTIVITY 2</string>
    <string name="a3">ACTIVITY 3</string>
    <string name="minijuegos">MINIGAMES</string>
    <string name="expvacc">VACCEO EXPERIENCE</string>
    <string name="juegosrol">ROLE GAMES</string>
    <string name="actividadesrol">ROLE ACTIVITIES</string>
    <string name="retomartest">RETAKE TEST</string>
    <string name="nivelfacil">EASY</string>
    <string name="nivelmedio">MEDIUM</string>
    <string name="niveldificil">HARD</string>
    <string name="seguirjugando">KEEP PLAYING</string>
</resources>